Have you ever wondered how you could
wake up a brain organoid? Yes, be brain
organoid. Tiny human brains that you can
grow in a literal jar if you want to
from human stem cells. They are in a
permanent sleep-like state. So, similar
to what we see in humans with delta
brain waves. Delta being what you would
expect for someone who is sleeping or
otherwise in a coma. But they do have
other brain waves. So, some researchers
decided to see what would happen if we
woke them up. Now, it is important to
note that this research group did not
use a phalamus organoid. And yes, you
can make one. You can even connect a
phalamus organoid to a cortex organoid.
Now, it's important to note that the
phalamus is part of your brain that's
responsible for wakefulness or
consciousness in the medical term. It's
also a sensory relay organ. So, it goes
through your thealamus and then is
spread to other parts of your brain.
Your cortex is typically what we think
of with conscious thought. The cortex is
the outer area of the brain and it's
responsible for higher order thinking. A
lot of the brain organoids that we see
that are doing things like playing pong
or operating robots are cortex
organoids, but there's no reason that
you have to stay with cortex. In the
case of waking them up, they gave them
hormones that would normally wake people
up, things that are associated with that
state. And yes, they did have brain
waves that were more associated with a
conscious state. And after 24 hours,
they went back to a sleep-like state.
Yes, your brain needs to sleep. The
individual cells need to sleep. They
can't keep firing forever. What this
study did not do is pop them into a
video game and see how well they played
in awakeful state versus a sleep state.
And yes, it seems to be similar to what
we think of with REM sleep, but it is
not REM sleep because they don't have
eyes for start. Well, some of them have
eyes. It's just not as complex as we
would think of in a adult human brain.
Oh, but this group connected a phalamus
to a cortex organoid and it worked. Now,
the specific reason that they would want
to do this is to study development. Yes,
we've studied development in mice, but
you can't really watch a human brain
develop and see how the different parts
interact with each other unless it's
outside a skull and you grow it in a
jar. Okay? It's usually done in a petri
dish or right over an electrode. But you
can grow them in a jar and that's what
matters to me at least. What you are
looking at is different loes of a brain
organoid. Now what they found is that if
you grow the fetal version of a brain in
a petri dish and you add the phalamus,
the phalamus actually directs the growth
of the cortex with both they actually
develop more quickly and develop into
being more mature. Typically the
transcriptto so the kinds of proteins
that the brain organoid will make does
match very closely to the gestational
age of a human. And then if you grow
them beyond that point to a year or 5
years, the protein signatures will match
say a 5-year-old child after 5 years,
but they do remain rather basic and
tiny, a few millimeters of grass. Now,
what researchers are really doing with
this is not quite as spooky as it
actually sounds. They're trying to make
a model for a person so that it can be
studied. Okay, that didn't help, did it?
That still sounds creepy. Essentially,
it's an alternative to using lab animals
or people and allows us to have a really
good view into early development or even
the study of diseases without ever
having to use a person. You can also
carefully change conditions. Whereas, if
you're doing a study group, yeah, you
got to care about people. Now, this is
the point where I'm going to get a
little bit more serious because there
are very real concerns about the ethics
of experimenting on brain organoids if
we make them increasingly complex or if
they have the capacity to feel pain,
which you know these assemblies did. I
covered these guys before. Now, these
guys actually did give them pain, a
sensory experience. They gave them the
ability to sense the heat from pepper.
So, capsin receptors. But as may seem
obvious, if we give them the capacity to
have sensory relay through a phalamus
and we give them the capacity to have
sensation, those two things can be
combined. We can create increasingly
complex brain organoids. It yeah also
could run robots, which has been done.
But that early research done in brain
organoids controlling robots like our
spider robot friend, it's done with
ordered and disordered signals because
brain organoids prefer order and they
don't like disorder. But we could give
them actual sensation using carbon
fibers that can translate light directly
into electrical signals which could
interface with their brain organoid and
give them a true sensory experience with
having a phalamus. And yes, you can give
them a organoid spinal cord. But again,
this is more the mad science of this
kind of stuff and I do love it. But it's
not the main focus. The main focus is
medical research and understanding
development. But main focus does not
mean the only focus because I really
want to see what happens. I know it's
not morally great and I'm not even
entirely sure why it's not morally
great, but it does feel wrong. Either
way, I will not look away. I will
continue to watch with horrified
fascination. Follow for more.